<znai>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs#klass</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Klass</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle></pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle></chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle>Klass</pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>Klass is a rapid application development framework for Java with first class support for temporal data.

## Overview

Klass generates a complete application stack from a concise domain model definition, including:

- Database schema
- POJOs and DTOs
- REST services
- GraphQL endpoints
- Admin UI

## Guide structure

This guide walks through building a realistic subset of Stack Overflow functionality to demonstrate the framework's capabilities.

The guide is organized into several parts:

- **Vision** - Core concepts including classes, associations, projections, and services
- **Audit Data** - Temporal data modeling and audited services
- **Bootstrapped Metamodel** - Dynamic querying and UI generation
- **Additional Features** - Enumerations, parameterized properties, and aggregations
- **Alternative Implementations** - Minimal viable product discussion
- **Related Works** - Comparison with similar technologies

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/vision/overview</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Overview [Vision]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Overview</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Vision</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Scope

This document covers long-term vision. A shorter-term, **minimal-viable-product** is discussed in [alternative implementations](alternative-implementations/overview).

This covers one set of implementation choices. **Alternatives** are discussed in [alternative implementations](alternative-implementations/overview).

**Related works** are discussed in [related works](related-works/overview).

## Running example

To demonstrate the framework's capabilities, we will walk through building a realistic subset of Stack Overflow functionality.

## Getting started

First, run the maven archetype.

```bash
mvn archetype:generate \
  -DarchetypeGroupId=com.klass \
  -DarchetypeArtifactId=klass-maven-archetype \
  -DinteractiveMode=false \
  -DgroupId=com.stackoverflow \
  -DartifactId=stackoverflow \
  -Dversion=1.0.0 \
  -Dpackage=com.stackoverflow \
  -Dname=StackOverflow
```

This command creates a new project in `./stackoverflow/`. The project compiles and runs, but doesn't yet do anything interesting.

## Model

The model was generated in `./stackoverflow/stackoverflow-domain-model/src/main/resources/com/stackoverflow/stackoverflow.klass`. It is nearly empty except for the package declaration.

An Klass model consists of classes, enumerations, associations, projections, and services.

The **classes**, **enumerations**, and **associations** make up the data model. From the data model, Klass generates a database schema, POJOs, DTOs, example data, etc. We will define the `Question` and `Answer` classes, as well as the one-to-many association between questions and answers.

**Services** are traditional http or rpc services. We will define a service to get a `Question` by its id.

**Projections** map services to data. They answer how much data a service reads or writes; conceptually how far the service walks through the object graph. For example, when we fetch a `Question` by its id, should we return the title and the body, or just the title? Should we include the question's answers in the response?

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/vision/classes</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Classes [Vision]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Classes</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Vision</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Classes

Let's add the classes `Question` and `Answer` to the model in stackoverflow.klass.

### Question

```klass
class Question
{
    id        : Long key id;
    title     : String minLength(15) maxLength(150);
    body      : String maxLength(30000);
}
```

**`id`** has the primitive type `Long`. The `key` modifier is similar to a database's primary key. The `id` modifier on the `id` property means that it's an auto-incrementing number, not a natural key.

**`title`** has the primitive type `String` with max length 150.

**`body`** has the primitive type `String` with max length 30000.

So far, this exactly matches the real Stack Overflow.

### Answer

```klass
class Answer
{
    id        : Long key id;
    body      : String(30000);
    questionId: Long private;
}
```

`Answer` also has **`id`** and **`body`** but no `title`.

`Answer` has **`questionId`** with the `private` modifier. It's private to the data-layer; it will be used as a foreign key. Private properties cannot appear in projections, so `questionId` won't be part of service bodies; neither request bodies nor response bodies.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/vision/associations</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Associations [Vision]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Associations</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Vision</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Associations

Let's add the one-to-many association between questions and answers.

```klass
association QuestionHasAnswer
{
    question: Question[1..1] final;
    answers: Answer[0..*];

    relationship this.id == Answer.questionId
}
```

Associations have two ends, and a direction.

The source end is named **`question`** and has type `Question`. The lower-bound of the multiplicity is `1` and the upper bound is also `1`.

The target end is named **`answers`** and has type `Answer`. The lower-bound of the multiplicity is `0` and the upper bound is `*` which means "many".

`Question[1..1]` means that every answer *requires* a question. An optional, or nullable property has the multiplicity `[0..1]`. The syntax `[1]` is shorthand for `[1..1]`.

`Answer[0..*]` means that every question has many answers, and that the set of answers is allowed to be empty. A non-empty set has the multiplicity `[1..*]`. The syntax `[*]` is shorthand for `[0..*]`.

Colloquially, we call this a one-to-many relationship. Keep in mind that this shorthand is vague. It only refers to the *upper-bounds* of the association ends.

Klass doesn't enforce singular and plural names. Take care to use singular names for to-one ends and plural names for to-many ends.

The `question` end has the modifier `final` which means that an answer cannot be repointed to a different question. In the data layer, this means the foreign key `questionId` is immutable. It doesn't mean that the question's text is immutable.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/vision/projections-and-services</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Projections And Services [Vision]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Projections And Services</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Vision</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Projections and Services

Let's add the service to fetch a question by its id.

### Service

```klass
service QuestionResource
{
    read getById(questionId: Long[1..1] id path): QuestionReadProjection[1]
    {
        url      : /question/{questionId: Long[1..1] id};
        criteria : this.id == questionId;
        format   : json;
    }
}
```

- Read operations translate to the `GET` verb when using http.
- We'll be able to `GET` `/api/question/1` to fetch the Question with id 1.
- The response will be json.
- The return multiplicity is one, so the response body will be a json object, not a json array.
- The criteria matches `Question.id` against the path parameter `questionId`, like the sql `where q.id = ?`
- The projection defines how much data will get serialized in the response body.

### Projection

The service referred to the projection `QuestionReadProjection` without defining it. Let's do that now.

```klass
projection QuestionReadProjection on Question
{
    id     : "Question id",
    title  : "Question title",
    body   : "Question body",

    answers:
    {
        id  : "Answer id",
        body: "Answer body",
    },
}
```

This projection includes everything; all of the question's properties including its answers, and all of the answers' properties. We do want everything included in the service's json response, but if we didn't we could remove parts to shrink the response.

### JSON Format

Since the service definition includes `format: json`, the response body will match the nested structure of the projection, and the projection's header names will be ignored.


### CSV Format

If the service definition included `format: csv` instead, then the nested structure would be flattened and the header names would become column headers in the response. The order of the columns would be defined by the order they appear in the projection definition from top-to-bottom, which is depth-first.

```csv
"Question id", "Question title"  , "Question body"  , "Answer id", "Answer body"
            1, "Question title 1", "Question body 1",           1, "Answer body 1"
            1, "Question title 1", "Question body 1",           2, "Answer body 2"
```

Note that to-many association ends get flattened, so the data for question 1 appears twice.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/audit-data/overview#audit-data</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Overview, Audit Data [Audit Data]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Overview</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Audit Data</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle>Audit Data</pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>So far, we've built a simple read service. We could add create, update, and delete and we'd have a "simple crud" version of Stack Overflow. But the real Stack Overflow services are more advanced. All updates and deletes are *non-destructive*. When you edit a question or answer, you can still view all of its old versions.

## Versions

[Here's a real example](https://stackoverflow.com/a/49938998) from Stack Overflow. The answer has 3 versions, at the time of writing. The url returns the latest version. There's a link with text like ["edited Apr 20 at 10:10"](https://stackoverflow.com/posts/49938998/revisions) which you can follow to see all versions. Each version has a number, a timestamp, the author's username, and the full text of the answer at the time.

## Optimistic locking

Imagine that two users click [Edit](https://stackoverflow.com/questions/49938832/did-eclipse-collections-get-deprecated-by-java-8/49938998#49938998) at the same time, make changes, and click "Save Edits". Without a carefully designed api, whoever saves second could silently overwrite the changes of the first. Stack Overflow uses version numbers to implement optimistic locking. Each mutating service takes the edited text, plus the version number that the edit applies to. In this example, the second user would get an error message saying something about attempting to edit version 3, while the current version is 4. They'd then have an opportunity to view the new edits and retry against the new version.

## Audit features

Klass treats these as separate features, which build upon each other.

- **Temporal milestoning** makes edits non-destructive, and adds the active time ranges to each piece of data.
- **Versioning** adds simple version numbers (1, 2, 3, ...) to each active time range. Versioned data must be temporally milestoned.
- **Auditing** adds tracking of the created-by author, last-updated-by author, and created-on time. Audited data must be temporally milestoned.
- **Optimistic locking** enhances "mutating" services to expect a version parameter, and to fail with a helpful error message on stale versions. Optimistically locked data must be versioned.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/audit-data/audit-model</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Audit Model [Audit Data]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Audit Model</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Audit Data</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Audit Model

All four features are activated using classifier modifiers.

```klass
class Question
    systemTemporal
    versioned
    audited
{
    // ...
}
```

Most classifier modifiers are compiler macros that are shorthand for a longer syntax that you could write out if desired.

### systemTemporal

The modifier `systemTemporal` is shorthand for adding three properties.

```klass
class Question
{
    // ...
    system    : TemporalRange system;
    systemFrom: TemporalInstant system from;
    systemTo  : TemporalInstant system to;
}
```

`systemFrom` and `systemTo` become part of the data layer. `system` is a synthetic property used in queries and criteria.

Relationships between two `systemTemporal` classes also implicitly include an equality clause between their `system` properties.

```klass
association QuestionHasAnswer
{
    question: Question[1..1] final;
    answers: Answer[0..*];

    relationship (this.id == Answer.questionId)
        &amp;&amp; this.system == Answer.system // The additional clause
}
```

### versioned

The modifier `versioned` is shorthand for adding a new version class and an association to it.

```klass
class QuestionVersion
    systemTemporal
{
    id    : Long key;
    // version modifier indicates the property holding the version number
    number: Integer version;
}

association QuestionHasVersion
{
    question: Question[1..1];
    version : QuestionVersion[1..1] owned version;

    relationship this.id == QuestionVersion.id
}
```

### audited

Auditing means keeping track of who made which modifications. To use auditing, there must be a `user` class. There may only be a single `user` class in the model.

```klass
// keyword `user` instead of `class`
user User
    systemTemporal
{
    // user class must have a single String key userId
    userId   : String key userId;
    // All other properties must be optional
    firstName: String?;
    lastName : String?;
    email    : String?;
}
```

The modifier `audited` is shorthand for adding three properties and two parameterized properties. If the class is `versioned`, the version class gets the same properties.

```klass
class Question
    systemTemporal
{
    // ...
    createdById       : String private createdBy;
    createdOn         : Instant createdOn;
    lastUpdatedById   : String private lastUpdatedBy;

    // A parameterized-property. Gives the User instead of the userId
    createdBy(): User[1..1] createdBy
    {
        this.createdById == User.userId
    }

    lastUpdatedBy(): User[1..1] lastUpdatedBy
    {
        this.lastUpdatedById == User.userId
    }
}

class QuestionVersion
    systemTemporal
{
    id             : Long key;
    number         : Integer version;
    createdById    : String private createdBy;
    createdOn      : Instant createdOn;
    lastUpdatedById: String private lastUpdatedBy;

    createdBy(): User[1..1] createdBy
    {
        this.createdById == User.userId
    }

    lastUpdatedBy(): User[1..1] lastUpdatedBy
    {
        this.lastUpdatedById == User.userId
    }
}

```

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/audit-data/audited-services</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Audited Services [Audit Data]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Audited Services</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Audit Data</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Audited Services

Stack Overflow allows collaborative editing. Let's walk through an example where Alice creates a new question and Bob edits the text. Since all audit features are on, both versions of the question are retained and can be fetched through services.

### Create

Alice POSTs a new question to `/api/question` on December 31.


She gets back 201 Created and a location header Location: http://.../api/question/1.

She can GET http://.../api/question/1 to get the full body.


- `id` was set to 1. The next created question will be 2. The next Answer will be 1. Each type gets its own sequence.
- `systemFrom` was set to December 31. `systemTo` is null, indicating that there is no phase-out time; that this data is currently active.
- `createdOn` matches `systemFrom` for now.
- `createdById` matches `lastUpdatedById` for now.
- The audit properties appear duplicated on the version.

### Update

Bob PUTs a new version to `/api/question/1` the next day, on January 1.


The version number is present and matches, so the edit succeeds. He gets back 204 No Content.

He can GET http://.../api/question/1 to get the full body.


- `systemFrom` was set to January 1. `systemTo` is null again.
- Version 1 (which we'll look at next) had its `systemTo` updated to the same time, January 1.
- The version number was updated to 2.
- `lastUpdatedById` was updated to Bob.
- `createdById` and `createdOn` are unchanged.

### Read by version

To read old versions, we can enhance the read service with an *optional* version parameter and an optional criteria.

```klass
service QuestionResource
{
    getById(id: Long[1..1]): QuestionReadProjection[0..1]
    {
        operation       : read;
        url             : /question/{id: Long[1..1]}?{version: Integer[0..1] version};
        criteria        : this.id == id;
        optionalCriteria: this.version.number == version
        format          : json;
    }
}
```

Leaving off the version query parameter would give the latest version. But now we can GET http://.../api/question/1?version=1 to see the previous version.


Everything is identical as when Alice first created it, except for `systemTo`. It started as `null` and was changed to January 1, the time version 2 was created.

`systemTemporal` turns the data store into an immutable append-only log. The **only** in-place updates are to `systemTo` and the only possible edit is to phase out a version (by changing `systemTo` from `null` to the current instant) while simultaneously phasing in a new version at the same instant. Or, in the case of a delete, not phasing in any new version.

### Read by time

While it's usually more convenient to deal with version numbers, we can also query for old versions by time.

```klass
service Question
{
    getById(id: Long[1..1]): QuestionReadProjection[0..1]
    {
        operation       : read;
        url             : /question/{id: Long[1..1]}?{version: Integer[0..1] version}&amp;{system: TemporalRange[0..1] system};
        criteria        : this.id == id;
        optionalCriteria: this.version.number == version
        optionalCriteria: this.system == system
        format          : json;
    }
}
```

Now we can GET http://.../api/question/1?system=2018-01-01T00:00:00.000Z to see the previous version.

Time ranges are inclusive on the `from` end and exclusive on the `to` end. So any time within the range `[2017-12-31T23:59:59.000Z, 2018-01-01T23:59:59.000Z)` would return the first version.

The time range check is fairly complex at the data layer. If we're querying for the current version (the system parameter is not provided or is null) then we have to check that systemTo is also null. Otherwise we have to check that the system parameter falls between systemFrom and systemTo, also taking into account the fact that systemTo may be null. We could have defined the additional criteria like this:

```ReladomoOperation
this.systemTo == null &amp;&amp; system == null
  || system != null
    &amp;&amp; this.systemFrom &lt;= system
    &amp;&amp; (this.systemTo == null || system &lt; this.systemTo)
```

The synthetic property `system` exists to simplify criteria like this, and to use in association criteria as described in [Audit Model](audit-data/audit-model#systemtemporal). Thus we're able to simplify the optionalCriteria to just `this.system == system`.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/bootstrapped-metamodel/overview#bootstrapped-metamodel</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Overview, Bootstrapped Metamodel [Bootstrapped Metamodel]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Overview</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>Klass has a metamodel; a model of models. In fact, it has several representations of the same metamodel.

- The Abstract Syntax Tree used internally by the compiler.
- The in-memory DomainModel object returned upon successful compilation.
- The bootstrapped metamodel.
- etc.

The bootstrapped metamodel is expressed like a regular model. The first few meta-types are defined like this:

```klass
package klass.model.meta.domain

interface Element
{
}

interface NamedElement
    implements Element
{
    name: String key maximumLength(256);
    ordinal: Integer private;
}

class PackageableElement
    abstract
    implements NamedElement
{
    packageName: String maximumLength(100000);
}

class Classifier
    abstract
    extends PackageableElement
{
}

class Klass
    extends Classifier
{
    superClassName: String? private maximumLength(256);
    abstractClass: Boolean;
}

enumeration PrimitiveType
{
    INTEGER("Integer"),
    LONG("Long"),
    DOUBLE("Double"),
    FLOAT("Float"),
    BOOLEAN("Boolean"),
    STRING("String"),
    INSTANT("Instant"),
    LOCAL_DATE("LocalDate"),
    TEMPORAL_INSTANT("TemporalInstant"),
    TEMPORAL_RANGE("TemporalRange"),
}

enumeration Multiplicity
{
    ZERO_TO_ONE("0..1"),
    ONE_TO_ONE("1..1"),
    ZERO_TO_MANY("0..*"),
    ONE_TO_MANY("1..*"),
}

class DataTypeProperty
    abstract
    implements NamedElement
{
    classifierName                : String key maximumLength(256);
    optional                      : Boolean;
}

class PrimitiveProperty
    extends DataTypeProperty
{
    primitiveType                 : PrimitiveType maximumLength(256);
}

association ClassifierHasDataTypeTypeProperties
{
    owningClassifier              : Classifier[1..1];
    dataTypeProperties            : DataTypeProperty[0..*] owned
        orderBy: this.ordinal ascending;
}
```

The full source is too large to include here. It defines enumeration, class, association, projection, and service, plus their parts.

The bootstrapped metamodel allows us to work with metadata like regular data. It defines some projections and services which return model data. For example, here's the service to get a class by its name:

```klass
package klass.model.meta.domain

projection KlassProjection on Klass
{
    name: "NamedElement name",
    packageName: "PackageableElement packageName",
    abstractClass: "Klass abstractClass",
    superInterfaces: ClassifierInterfaceMappingProjection,
    classifierModifiers: ClassifierModifierProjection,
    dataTypeProperties: DataTypePropertyProjection,
    superClass: {
        name: "NamedElement name",
    },
    associationEnds: {
        name: "NamedElement name",
    },
    parameterizedProperties: ParameterizedPropertyProjection,
}

service KlassResource on Klass
{
    /meta/class/{name: String[1..1]}
        GET
        {
            multiplicity: one;
            criteria    : this.name == name;
            projection  : KlassProjection;
        }
    /meta/class
        GET
        {
            multiplicity: many;
            criteria    : all;
            projection  : KlassProjection;
            orderBy     : this.ordinal ascending;
        }
}
```

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/bootstrapped-metamodel/bootstrapped-model-data</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Bootstrapped Model Data [Bootstrapped Metamodel]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Bootstrapped Model Data</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Bootstrapped Model Data

The Klass metamodel is part of every Klass model. When a Klass application starts, it "bootstraps" the metamodel by populating model data into the data store. This means that in the Stack Overflow application, we can GET `/api/meta/class/Question` to get the Question class as data.


</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/bootstrapped-metamodel/bootstrapped-meta-model-data</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Bootstrapped Meta Model Data [Bootstrapped Metamodel]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Bootstrapped Meta Model Data</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Bootstrapped Metamodel Data

Since the metamodel is part of the model, the bootstrap process populates metamodel types too. This means that we can GET `/api/meta/class/Klass` for the Klass class in any application.


</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/bootstrapped-metamodel/dynamic-query</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Dynamic Query [Bootstrapped Metamodel]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Dynamic Query</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Dynamic Query

In a production application, we only enable modeled services. In development, it can be useful to allow dynamic queries.

The dynamic query endpoint is a service that accepts a dynamic projection and criteria as a request body. The format is very similar to the serialized form of a projection or service from the bootstrapped metamodel.

Say we wanted to query for all questions that start with the words "Why do". We could POST `/api/meta/query/json`:


There's also a form that uses GET, to allow easier experimentation from the browser. The same query can be encoded as query parameters.

`/api/meta/query/json/Question?multiplicity=many&amp;criteria=this.title startsWith "Why do"&amp;include=this.title`

If there's an existing projection that you want to reuse, you can just refer to it by name.


</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/bootstrapped-metamodel/dynamic-ui</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Dynamic Ui [Bootstrapped Metamodel]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Dynamic Ui</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Dynamic UI

Production UI components are code-generated, but the dynamic UI used in development is static JavaScript.

The UI fetches the domain model from the meta-services. It renders dynamic forms for querying and editing based on classes and their data-type properties.

The dynamic projection builder uses classes and all their properties, including association ends. The root node represents a class. Leaf nodes are data-type properties or association ends that are not included in the projection. Inner nodes are association ends that *are* included in the projection.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/bootstrapped-metamodel/dynamic-model</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Dynamic Model [Bootstrapped Metamodel]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Dynamic Model</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Bootstrapped Metamodel</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle></pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Dynamic Model

We can fetch the bootstrapped model with a GET against the /api/meta services. For projections and services only, we can also create new ones by POSTing to the same urls.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/additional-features/overview#additional-features</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Overview, Additional Features [Additional Features]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Overview</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Additional Features</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle>Additional Features</pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>In this section, we'll continue the Stack Overflow example and implement up/down votes on Questions.

We'll explore enumerations, parameterized properties, parameterized projections, and aggregations.

## Enumerations

We'll start with an enumeration to indicate the direction of a vote.

```klass
enumeration VoteDirection
{
    UP("up"),
    DOWN("down"),
}
```

The upper-case literal names are used within the model. The quoted strings are pretty names that will appear in service request and response bodies.

## Partial inference, composite keys

Next we'll define the vote class.

```klass
class QuestionVote
    systemTemporal
    audited
{
    questionId : Long key;
    createdById: String key createdBy;
    direction  : VoteDirection;
}
```

Stack Overflow [restricts voting](https://meta.stackexchange.com/a/5213/147927) based on how many times you've voted and whether the post was edited since the last vote. So votes must be `systemTemporal`.

Votes must be `audited`, to keep track of who cast the vote.

A user can only cast one vote, so the key should be (questionId, createdById). There is no auto-generated `id` property. `QuestionVote` has a natural, composite key.

Normally, we'd allow the `createdById` property to be inferred based on the `audited` keyword, but then it would be inferred without the `key` modifier.

A user cannot upvote and downvote the same question, so `direction` is not part of the key.

## Associations

```klass
association QuestionHasVotes
{
    question: Question[1..1] final;
    votes: QuestionVote[0..*];

    relationship this.id == QuestionVote.questionId
}

association UserHasQuestionVotes
{
    user: User[1..1] final;
    votes: QuestionVote[0..*];

    relationship this.userId == QuestionVote.createdById
}
```

A vote is like many-to-many mapping from Question to User.

## Services

We'll create an upsert service for creating and editing votes. No create service is necessary because there's no auto-incrementing id.

```klass
service QuestionVoteResource
{
    upsert upsertQuestionVote(
        questionId: Long[1..1] path,
        user: User[1..1] user,
        questionVote: QuestionVote[1] body)
    {
        // service : http;

        url     : /question/vote/{questionId: Long[1..1]};

        criteria: this.question.id == questionId &amp;&amp; this.createdById == user.userId;

        after   : this.question.createdById != user.userId
            &amp;&amp; (this.createdOn > now - (5 * 60 * 1000)
                || this.systemFrom &lt; this.question.systemFrom);
    }

    upsert upsertQuestionVote(
        questionVote: QuestionVote[1] body,
        user: User[1..1] user)
    {
        // service : rpc;

        url     : /question/vote;

        criteria: this.question.id == questionVote.question.id &amp;&amp; this.createdById == user.userId;

        after   : this.question.createdById != user.userId
            &amp;&amp; (this.createdOn > now - (5 * 60 * 1000)
                || this.systemFrom &lt; this.question.systemFrom);
    }

    /question/vote/{questionId: Long[1..1]}
        PUT
        {
            multiplicity: one;
            criteria    : this.questionId == questionId &amp;&amp; this.createdById == userId;
            validate    : this.question.createdById != userId
                &amp;&amp; (this == null
                || this.createdOn > now - (5 * 60 * 1000)
                || this.systemFrom &lt; this.question.systemFrom);
            projection  : QuestionVoteWriteProjection;
        }
}
```

The main criteria uses the global `userId` which is the name of the currently logged in principal.

The validation criteria uses the global `now`, less 5 minutes in milliseconds, to check whether the vote was created within the last 5 minutes.

```klass
service QuestionVote
{
    /question/vote/{questionId: Long[1..1]}
        // PUT ...
        DELETE
        {
            multiplicity: one;
            criteria    : this.questionId == questionId &amp;&amp; this.createdById == userId;
            validate    : this.createdOn > now - (5 * 60 * 1000)
                    || this.systemFrom &lt; this.question.systemFrom);
            projection  : QuestionVoteWriteProjection;
        }
}
```

The DELETE service is very similar. It just doesn't need to validate that the vote exists, and it doesn't need to validate that the voter and the question author are different users.

## Parameterized properties

When viewing a question on Stack Overflow, you can see your own vote if you've cast one.

```klass
class Question
    systemTemporal
    versioned
    audited
{
    // ...

    myVote(): QuestionVote[0..1]
    {
        this.votes.createdById == userId
    }
}
```

We add `myVote()` as a parameterized property, though there are no parameters in this example. This criteria is another example using the global `userId`. Once the parameterized property is defined, it can be included in a projection using the same syntax as an association end. In fact, a parameterized property without any parameters can be thought of as a uni-directional association.

## Parameterized projections

The definition of `myVote()` above is fine, and fairly similar to the `upvoted` and `downvoted` properties in [the real StackOverflow api](https://api.stackexchange.com/docs/types/question).

However, let's add some perhaps unrealistic variants that take parameters, just to see what parameterized properties can do.

```klass
class Question
    systemTemporal
    versioned
    audited
{
    // ...

    votesByDirection(direction: VoteDirection[1..1]): QuestionVote[0..*]
    {
        this.votes.direction == direction
    }

    voteByUser(userId: String[1..1] userId): QuestionVote[0..1]
    {
        // userId refers to the parameter, not the global
        this.votes.createdById == userId
    }
}
```

Parameterized properties can be included in read projections. There are two ways to provide the parameter, as a constant or as a projection parameter.

Here we define a projection that parameterizes `votesByDirection` twice, once for each `VoteDirection`.

```klass
projection ProjectionWithConstant on Question
{
    id             : "Question id",
    title          : "Question title",
    body           : "Question body",

    votesByDirection("up"):
    {
        // This would work, but the information is redundant
        // direction: "Upvote direction",
        user: {
            userId: "Upvote user id",
        },
    },

    votesByDirection("down"):
    {
        // This would work, but the information is redundant
        // direction: "Upvote direction",
        user: {
            userId: "Upvote user id",
        },
    },
}
```

Here we define a parameterized projection, that passes its parameter through to `voteByUser`.

```klass
projection ProjectionWithParameter(userId: String[1..1] userId) on Question
{
    id             : "Question id",
    title          : "Question title",
    body           : "Question body",

    voteByUser(userId):
    {
        direction: "Vote direction",
        // This would work, but the information is redundant
        /*
        user: {
            userId: "Vote user id",
        },
        */
    }
}
```

### Parameterized service

When using a parameterized projection, the service must also be parameterized.

```klass
service Question
{
    /question/{id: Long[1..1]}/{userId: String[1..1] userId}
        GET
        {
            format      : json;
            multiplicity: one;
            criteria    : this.id == id;
            projection  : ProjectionWithParameter(userId);
        }
}
```

### Parameterized responses

When a json response includes parameterized properties, the parameters become part of the field names.


## Aggregations

[StackOverflow's documentation](https://stackoverflow.com/help/privileges/established-user) states:

> Voting scores, as displayed, are the sum of the up and down votes on a post. Vote counts are the individual up and down votes that make up the score.

You can view the vote counts by clicking on the score of a post. This will break the score into upvotes and downvotes.

We add two aggregation properties to Question; `upvotes` and `downvotes`.

```klass
class Question
    systemTemporal
    versioned
    audited
{
    // ...

    upvotes: Integer
    {
        count(this.votes.direction == VoteDirection.UP)
    }

    downvotes: Integer
    {
        count(this.votes.direction == VoteDirection.DOWN)
    }
}
```

Associations and parameterized properties are defined using criteria. Aggregation properties are defined using a fuller expression language. These aggregations use the `count()` function. Other available functions include `sum()`, `min()`, `max()`, and `average()`.

Once these aggregation properties are defined in a class, they can be included in read projections like normal properties. They cannot be included in write projections.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/alternative-implementations/overview#alternative-implementation-choices</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Overview, Alternative implementation choices [Alternative Implementations]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Overview</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Alternative Implementations</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle>Alternative implementation choices</pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## One-time generation

Instead of a maven archetype, initial project creation could be done with:

- [Yeoman](http://yeoman.io/).
- A webapp that produces a zip for download, like [Spring Initializr](https://start.spring.io/) for Spring Boot.
- A custom CLI, possibly in python.

## Metamodel

Instead of a new metamodel, Klass could use an existing metamodel like [Eclipse Modeling Framework's ECore](https://www.eclipse.org/modeling/emf/).

ECore is a fairly complete implementation of UML, with all its warts. ECore also has enhancements to allow it to represent anything expressible in Java, including Generics.

Klass's metamodel is a fairly narrow subset of UML. It addresses some weaknesses in UML, such as the lack of a type hierarchy between the various types of properties.

Klass's metamodel also includes projections and services.

## Metamodel language

Instead of a new DSL, the model could be expressed using:

- [OpenAPI vendor extensions](https://swagger.io/docs/specification/openapi-extensions/) (maybe, unproven)
- A data format that's not a DSL, like JSON, YML, or XML, conforming to a JSON schema or XSD.
- Annotations inside a Java or Python program.
- A graphical language like UML.

## Data Store

Rather than a relational database, the data could be stored in:

- A specific non-relational store, like a documentation database or a graph database.
- An abstract DataStore interface, with multiple implementations.

## Audit Data

Rather than storing phased-out data in the same tables as active data, they could be stored in separate audit tables.

This would improve the performance of queries for active data. It would complicate querying for previous versions, especially when those versions have relationships to data that is still active.

## Relationship criteria

The docs show a syntax for relationship criteria that is similar to a sql join.

```klass
relationship this.id == Answer.questionId
```

It's possible to use a syntax where a property is annotated as a foreign key instead.

It's possible to use a syntax where a foreign key tuple is listed instead.

However, parameterized properties would need a more powerful syntax.

## Service syntax

The service syntax is url-centric. If we want to support both http and rpc, we may want a more flexible syntax.

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <url>/docs/related-works/overview#related-works</url>
    <fullTitle>Klass: Overview, Related Works [Related Works]</fullTitle>
    <pageTitle>Overview</pageTitle>
    <chapterTitle>Related Works</chapterTitle>
    <pageSectionTitle>Related Works</pageSectionTitle>
    <text>
      <score>STANDARD</score>
      <text>## Data mapping aggregators

Examples:

- Spark Catalyst / Spark SQL
- Hive

In Klass, the model, store, and mapping are all 1-1-1. These tools allow non-trivial mappings between the model and the store.

- Model: Clean domain model
- Store: A model still, but of the data store. Can be messy.
- Mapping: Which tables, columns, etc. map to which part of the clean model. How to perform joins, aggregations.

Systems that support non-trivial mappings tend to be read-only. The mappings are lossy transformations. For example, not every column may be mapped into the model. Or a property may be the result of an aggregation. So there's no obvious way to write through the model.

These systems are powerful analytical tools. Catalyst is a powerful query engine, with advanced planning and routing.

Read-write systems can't support complex mappings, but can rely on the data store for efficient query execution.

## OpenAPI

### Things to like

- [SwaggerHub](https://swagger.io/tools/swaggerhub/) is a site for "Hosted, Interactive API Documentation".
- It's a great resource for developers to find and use a documented api.
- You could imagine it as the foundation for a service discovery mechanism.

### Drawbacks

- The OpenAPI model is tightly bound to http.
- It includes implementation details like numeric http codes.
- It cannot represent other service types like gRPC without vendor extensions.
- It cannot represent data layer concerns like keys, foreign keys, joins. It doesn't help with fetching data and serializing it to json.
- It cannot represent UI concerns like display names.

- [Relationships are uni-directional](https://swagger.io/docs/specification/data-models/data-types/).

- So a Question has answers, and Answer has a question, but nothing in the schema links these two properties.
- This is fine for json; and after all OpenAPI doesn't help you at the data layer.
- Bidirectional relationships are critical at the data layer, to know that a single foreign key `questionId` is used to perform the same join when navigating the relationship in either direction.

- Loose ecosystem of tools of varying quality.

- The OpenAPI specification and core tools like the Swagger editor are maintained by core contributors.
- The various code generators for different technologies have different maintainers and varying quality.
- The Jersey 2 generator, which is the most popular http variant for Java, has quality problems.
- Minor releases have produced breaking changes in both the code and the http api.
- Exception handling isn't done in Jersey's idiomatic way.
- Serializer plugins aren't done in Jersey's idiomatic way.

- The community's top contributors created a [hostile fork called openapi-generator](https://github.com/OpenAPITools/openapi-generator/blob/master/docs/qna.md).

- Some of the issues above, like breaking changes, were mentioned in the rationale.

## Spring Boot / JHipster

Spring Boot builds on top of Spring. JHipster builds on top of Spring Boot.

The Spring Boot stack is probably the most spiritually similar related work. There's plenty to like about it, and some drawbacks that may justify not using it.

### Things to like

- JHipster includes JDL, a spiritually similar DSL.
- [JDL-Studio](https://start.jhipster.tech/jdl-studio/) is a web-based IDE with syntax-highlighting and live-updating read-only UML diagrams.
- Relationships in JDL are bidirectional.
- [Relationships can be annotated with a display field](https://www.jhipster.tech/jdl/#relationshipdeclaration), which is "the name of the field that should show up in select boxes." For example, in an auto-generated form to create Answers, there may be a select box for which Question it answers. It should display `title`, rather than `id`.
- Spring Data supports many data stores.

### Drawbacks

- Every entity (class) gets an `id` property, which is an auto-incrementing integer. There are no natural keys.
- Spring Data has limited support for audit-data. It can track the version number, last updated time, and last updated user. However, all previous versions are lost.
- Hibernate Envers is an extension that is meant to be non-lossy. However:
- Envers is not integrated into Spring Boot / JHipster
- Envers keeps audit data in separate audit tables with a completely different schema. It is difficult to recreate previous state of anything other than a single vertex in isolation.
- Envers adds audit functionality, but doesn't disable Hibernate's destructive. You have to remember not to call update() and delete().

## GraphQL

[GraphQL](https://graphql.org/) is a query language for APIs. The ecosystem of frameworks that have developed around it can be considered related work.

GraphQL's query language is probably the closest thing in open source to Klass's projections.

### Things to like

- GraphQL's [query fields](https://graphql.org/learn/queries/#fields) are similar to Klass's read projections.
- The nested structure exactly matches the structure of the returned json.

- [Fields can take arguments](https://graphql.org/learn/queries/#arguments).

- This is another term for parameterized properties.
- This is a powerful technique for refining relationships.
- For example, we can refine the relationship between Question and Answer by declaring a field for a Question's answers by some user.

### Drawbacks

- [GraphQL's relationships](https://graphql.org/learn/schema/#object-types-and-fields) are uni-directional. So a Question has answers, and Answer has a question, but nothing in the schema links these two properties. This is fine for reads; and after all GraphQL started as just a query language. Bidirectional relationships are critical for writes. This is one reason why [dgraph's query language](https://docs.dgraph.io/master/query-language/) is GraphQL+-, which extends edge declarations with a [reverse edge](https://docs.dgraph.io/master/query-language/#reverse-edges).
- GraphQL makes it easy to express powerful queries for which there is no efficient execution plan.
- For example, a multi-hop graph walk with predicates that narrow the walk on each hop.
- The only possible implementation is to perform IO for every hop.
- GraphQL was invented to stitch together microservice responses into a cohesive subgraph. It assumes that a "foreign key" in one json response will lead to a GET against another service.

- GraphQL's responses are always json. There's no notion of flattening. GraphQL cannot return csv, [GraphML](http://graphml.graphdrawing.org/), etc.

- Mutations feel second class. The mutation bodies conform to a schema, but you're on your own for performing the mutation.

- It's common to expose a /graphql/ endpoint over http. While not as dangerous as exposing a /sql/ endpoint, it gives complete control to clients by default. It requires extra effort to handle some cross-cutting concerns like recording meaningful metrics, rate limiting, data-level entitlements, etc.

## Other related works

- EdgeDB
- Relay
- dgraph
- FOAM Framework
- TextUML

</text>
    </text>
  </entry>
</znai>
